{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man was legendarily forced to sell his belongings after his son Caeso fled to the Etruscans. Barbatus called upon this man to thwart Spurius Maelius’ plans to buy the crown of Rome in 439 BC. This man, who rose to his highest post after the Aequi attacked Tusculum, was victorious at the Battle of Mount Algidus, after which he chose to return to his farm and resigned his dictatorial powers just fifteen days after receiving them. For ten points, name this famously honorable Roman statesman who inspired the name of a city in Ohio.",
      "answer": "Lucius Quinctius Cincinnatus"
    },
    {
      "question": "A protest against this treaty in Hibiya Park resulted in 17 deaths and the destruction of over 300 buildings. A General Stores Building was the site of the negotiations of this treaty, whose delegates included Roman Rosen. In this treaty, the Liaodong Peninsula was ceded to a side represented by Komura Jutaro, while Port Arthur and half of Sakhalin were given to a country represented by Sergei Witte. Teddy Roosevelt helped mediate, for ten points, what 1905 treaty ending the Russo-Japanese War?",
      "answer": "Treaty of Portsmouth"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man argued that the infinite sin of Adam could only be atoned for by the infinite sacrifice of Jesus in Cur Deus Homo. The monk Gaunilo refuted one of this man’s ideas with the example of a mythical island. This man argued that God is the greatest possible being, and therefore must exist, in his Proslogion. The ontological argument was formulated by, for ten points, what saint who served as the Archbishop of Canterbury in the late 11th century?",
      "answer": "Saint Anselm of Canterbury"
    },
    {
      "question": "Min Chueh Chang helped Gregory Pincus create a product meant for this purpose. The Woman Rebel was written by an activist supporting this action who was prosecuted under the Federal Comstock Law. Diaphragms were illegally smuggled into the United States to aid with this action, which was promoted by a Brownsville clinic that opened in 1916. Margaret Sanger and Planned Parenthood advocate for, for ten points, what type of medical care that assists in family planning and can prevent abortions?",
      "answer": [
        "contraception",
        "birth control",
        "family planning before mentioned",
        "prompt on women’s medical care"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man deposed Alakeshwara of the Kotte Kingdom during a military expedition to Ceylon. He helped oversee the construction of the Porcelain Tower after he was reassigned as commander of Nanjing, after his influence waned under Hongxi [hong-shee]. This man’s most famous feats were performed under the Yongle Emperor, to whose court he brought a Malindi giraffe. For ten points, name this admiral of the Ming Dynasty known for his seven “treasure voyages.”",
      "answer": "Zheng He , but be lenient"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man heavily used the theme “Ashokan Farewell” in one of his works. This man focused on people like Everett Alvarez, Ambassador Bui Diem, and Tim O’Brien in a ten episode work that features his trademark style of slowly zooming away from a still image. Mathew Brady’s photographs and David McCulloch’s narration were praised in a 1990 work by, for ten points, what director of The Vietnam War, The Civil War, and several other documentary miniseries for television?",
      "answer": "Ken Burns"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader’s reputation suffered after being ambushed by Charles “No Flint” Grey in the Paoli Massacre, but he regained his prestige by leading a daring nighttime raid at the Battle of Stony Point. In this man’s most famous victory, he defeated the forces of the Western Confederacy and Blue Jacket, after which the Treaty of Greenville was signed. This man was sent by George Washington to subdue Native Americans in the Northwest Territory. For ten points, name this winner of the Battle of Fallen Timbers a Revolutionary-era brigadier general nicknamed “Mad Anthony.”",
      "answer": "“Mad” Anthony Wayne"
    },
    {
      "question": "The name of this state was inspired by the name of an island in a book by Garci Rodriguez de Montalvo. After landing near this state’s Point Reyes, an explorer gave the name “New Albion” to a region in this state. The Chumash were taken to pueblos to be taught Christianity after being transported from its Channel Islands. Vizcaino named several major cities in this state, including Monterey. El Camino Real passes between 21 missions in, for ten points, what western US state that underwent the Bear Flag Revolt?",
      "answer": "California"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle was preceded by a failed peace negotiation at the castle Montebello and the losing side’s failure to make new allies at Ciavenna. Wichmann of Magdeburg reinforced one side at Como prior to this battle. Guido da Landriano led a courageous defense of the cross of Aribert of Milan in this battle with the aid of the “Company of Death.” It led to the Treaty of Constance, where the Holy Roman Empire agreed not to interfere in Italian affairs. For ten points, name this 1176 battle in which the Lombard League defeated Frederick Barbarossa.",
      "answer": "Battle of Legnano"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this man’s administration, Jay Mazur chanted “We are one” at a rally in Columbus Park during the largest-ever strike in New York’s Chinatown. This man described another strike, involving an organization led by Robert Poli, as “a peril to national safety” and gave Poli’s group 48 hours to return to their jobs. PATCO was de-certified after striking under this president, who argued the strike was illegal. For ten points, name this president who clashed with the air traffic controller union in the 1980s.",
      "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Max Nordau promoted this movement in an address calling for a “muscular” version of its supporters. Ze’ev Jabotinsky founded a “revisionist” version of this movement with the creation of Betar. The Uganda Scheme tried to give up a portion of British East Africa in support of this movement. The Balfour Declaration, given to Lord Rothschild, reaffirmed this movement’s desire for aliyah. For ten points, name this movement that, at its creation in the 19th century, sought to establish a Jewish homeland in Israel.",
        "answer": "Zionism"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This activist founded the Zionist Organization at an 1897 conference in Switzerland and is often known as the “father” of modern Israel.",
        "answer": "Theodor Herzl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman was allegedly introduced to her husband by Aaron Burr, who frequented the boarding house run by this woman’s mother. This woman holds the distinction of being the only First Lady given an honorary Congressional seat. Because he was widowed, Thomas Jefferson often relied on this First Lady to serve as hostess during official events. For ten points, name this First Lady who directed her family’s slave to save the Landsdowne portrait of George Washington during the War of 1812.",
        "answer": [
          "Dolley Todd Madison",
          "Dolley Todd Payne"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This slave of the Madison family saved the Landsdowne portrait during the burning of Washington. Daniel Webster helped this man purchase his freedom, after which he published a White House memoir in 1865.",
        "answer": "Paul Jennings"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This deity seduced four dwarfs to acquire a fine gold necklace in the Olafs Saga, compiled by two Catholic priests in the late 1300s. Many names of North European flower species that were named for this goddess became named for the Virgin Mary. This member of the Vanir rules over Folkvangr, or the “army field,” where she received half of the men dying in combat, the other half going to Valhalla. For ten points, name this Norse goddess of fertility, love, and war.",
        "answer": "Freya or Freyja"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Stories of Freya are collected in, among other works, the Prose Edda, compiled by this 13th century Icelandic historian.",
        "answer": "Snorri Sturulson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A former member of this movement named Jeremiah Brandreth led the failed Pentrich Rising, which wanted to wipe out the national debt by starting an uprising in Derbyshire. This movement’s namesake, a weaver in Anstey, used a hammer in his most notorious act. The Frame Breaking Act of 1812 allowed the British government to execute seventy members of this movement, which began in Nottingham among textile workers worried about their job security. For ten points, name this 19th century movement that violently opposed innovation and lends its name to a modern term for people that do not embrace new technology.",
        "answer": "Luddites"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the supporters of the Luddites was this father of computer programming pioneer Ada Lovelace.",
        "answer": "Lord George Gordon Byron"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A woman who married into this family commissioned Julia Morgan to embellish a Mining Building named for her husband. Another member of this family hired Morgan to design a home for this family near San Simeon that includes space for what was the world’s largest private zoo. A Greek Theater named for this family is still in use on the University of California Berkeley campus, where a member of this family named Patty was kidnapped in 1974. For ten points, name this American family once headed by journalism magnate William Randolph.",
        "answer": [
          "Hearst",
          "Phoebe Elizabeth Apperson Hearst",
          "Patricia Campbell “Patty” Hearst",
          "William Randolph Hearst"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to designing many projects for the Hearst family, architect Julia Morgan designed several buildings for this organization, which was founded by Mary Jane Kinnaird and Emma Robarts to promote the empowerment of women.",
        "answer": [
          "World YWCA",
          "World Young Women’s Christian Association"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this state, Frank Canton led a band of Texans known as Wolcott’s Regulators in Powder River Country during the Johnston County War. Thomas J. Walsh led an investigation of a scandal named for a location in this state; as a result, Albert Fall was imprisoned for accepting bribes. The Teapot Dome oil field is in this state, where the Great Western Cattle Trail passed by Fort Laramie. The first state to grant suffrage to women was, for ten points, what state that is governed from Cheyenne?",
        "answer": "Wyoming"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Johnston County War ended after this President called in the cavalry. This man was elected in the last Presidential election in which Wyoming was a territory, not a state, and when he lost his re-election in the year of the Johnston County War, Populist candidate James Weaver carried four western states.",
        "answer": "Benjamin Harrison"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer wrote his choral piece Trois Chansons while waiting to be enlisted in the Air Force. This composer noted that “the dead are sad enough, in their eternal silence” when reflecting on his 1917 six-movement piece that pays memory to his deceased friends. After Paul Wittgenstein lost his right arm during World War I, this composer wrote a Piano Concerto for the Left Hand. A repetitive melody plays over a snare drum ostinato in a piece by, for ten points, what French composer of Le Tombeau de Couperin and Bolero?",
        "answer": "Maurice Ravel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ravel took influence from this French avant-garde composer who composed the ballet Parade during World War I and wrote three Gymnop´edies.",
        "answer": "Erik Satie"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man died on a diplomatic mission to Russia after his ship, the HMS Hampshire, hit a German mine. This man’s infighting with George Curzon caused Curzon to resign as Viceroy of India. This man agreed with Jean-Baptiste Marchand to fly three flags over an African fort during a tense territorial standoff in 1898. A 1914 recruitment poster demanded that this man “wants you” to join the army. Charles Gordon’s death was “avenged” by, for ten points, what British officer who won the 1898 Battle of Omdurman in Sudan?",
        "answer": "Horatio Herbert Kitchener, 1st Earl Kitchener"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Kitchener helped resolve this 1898 dispute between England and France over the Sudan through calm, restrained relations with his French counterpart, Jean-Baptiste Marchand. Britain’s massive troop advantage also helped ensure this incident did not explode into war.",
        "answer": "Fashoda incident or crisis, etc."
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "US vs. Nazi Germany",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Continent where the Nazi positions in Morocco were targeted in Operation Torch.",
          "answer": "Africa"
        },
        {
          "question": "French region where the Allies landed on D-Day.",
          "answer": "Normandy"
        },
        {
          "question": "One-word reply given by Anthony McAuliffe upon being told to surrender Bastogne.",
          "answer": "Nuts!"
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed dual operation to capture bridges in the Netherlands in 1944.",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Market Garden",
            "Market alone"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Rommel’s tanks won the Battle of Kasserine Pass against inexperienced US troops.",
          "answer": "Tunisia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amphibious operation, hidden by Operation Mincemeat, that caused Hitler to cancel an offensive at Kursk.",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Husky",
            "Allied invasion of Sicily Glyndwr Michael"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Northeast French city captured by Patton in November ‘44, perhaps better known for a fortress where Marshal Bazaine was besieged in 1870.",
          "answer": "Metz"
        },
        {
          "question": "Port city near Naples that was stormed by amphibious troops in Operation Avalanche on September 9, 1943.",
          "answer": "Salerno"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Peter the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country he led as tsar.",
          "answer": "Russian Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "European sea that he sought to control by building the city of Saint Petersburg.",
          "answer": "Baltic Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Members of the aristocracy who were forced to pay taxes on their beards.",
          "answer": "boyars"
        },
        {
          "question": "1698 uprising of infantrymen that was brutally put down by Peter.",
          "answer": "Streltsy uprising"
        },
        {
          "question": "Civil service hierarchy introduced by Peter in 1722 to create a bureaucracy devoted to him.",
          "answer": "Table of Ranks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Iranian dynasty that Peter fought in 1722-23; it collapsed a decade later.",
          "answer": "Safavid dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-Ottoman alliance he strengthened with his Grand Embassy; it dissolved with the Treaty of Karlowitz in 1699.",
          "answer": "Holy League"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cossack commander whose rebellion against Peter, the supposed Antichrist, sputtered after his 1708 death.",
          "answer": [
            "Kondraty Bulavin",
            "Bulavin Rebellion"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "20th Century Brazil",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Planned city built to be Brazil’s new capital in the 1950s.",
          "answer": "Brasilia"
        },
        {
          "question": "City replaced as capital in 1960.",
          "answer": "Rio de Janeiro"
        },
        {
          "question": "revolution.",
          "answer": [
            "coffee and milk",
            "caf´e com leite"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "State, named for Brazil’s most populous city, that dominated that two-state political system.",
          "answer": "Sao Paulo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Other, larger state in that two-state political system.",
          "answer": "Minas Gerais"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dictator who committed suicide in 1954 after ordering a hit on Carlos Lacerda.",
          "answer": "Getulio Vargas"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who authorized the new capital and led Brazil from 1956 to 1961.",
          "answer": "Juscelino Kubitschek"
        },
        {
          "question": "President ousted in the coup of 1930, which also prevented President-elect Ju´lio Prestes from taking power.",
          "answer": "Washington Luiz"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After a leader of this event was shot, his assassin declared that “I have killed a man, but I am not a murderer;” the courts eventually found Soghomon Tehlirian not guilty of that killing in Berlin. Operation Nemesis sought to assassinate Djemal and (20 pts)",
        "Talaat for this event after the two pashas marched their victims to Deir ez-Zor. The Battle of Sarikamish was blamed on a certain group aiding (10 pts)",
        "Russia in World War I, leading to, for ten points, what genocide perpetrated by the Ottoman government and denied by modern Turkey?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Armenian genocide",
        "Armenia alone after “genocide” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Singer Sargent painted this figure as portrayed by Ellen Terry, wearing a dress partially made of 1,000 beetle wings and crowning herself. The article “Muddle Instead of Music” in Pravda condemned Dimitri (20 pts)",
        "Shostakovich for an opera titled for this woman of the Mtsensk District. This queen attempts to wash her hands of imagined (10 pts)",
        "blood in the “Out, damned spot” scene of a 1606 play. For ten points, name this treacherous wife who encourages her husband to kill Duncan in Shakespeare’s “Scottish play.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Lady Macbeth"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) With Bill Nichols, this man sponsored a bill to reorganize the Department of Defense. This man’s policies were targeted by the “Ice Cream” Ad and another ad that ended “We must (20 pts)",
        "love each other, or we must die.” In one campaign, this man’s slogan “In your heart, you know he’s right” was mocked by his opponent’s slogan “In your gut, you know he’s nuts.” The book Conscience of a (10 pts)",
        "Conservative was written by, for ten points, what five-time senator from Arizona who lost in a landslide election to Lyndon Johnson in 1964?"
      ],
      "answer": "Barry Goldwater"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the 1980s, this country experienced a Mountain War in which Christians were displaced from its Chouf region. A massacre of a refugee camp in this country was conducted as retaliation for the assassination of Bachir (20 pts)",
        "Gemayel, who founded this country’s Phalangist party. The Taif Agreement ended a civil war in this country, where the Sabra and Shatila massacres occurred. The militant group (10 pts)",
        "Hezbollah is based in, for ten points, what country once led by Rafik Hariri, who was assassinated in Beirut?"
      ],
      "answer": "Lebanon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The world’s oldest Chinatown is this city’s township of Binondo, a district originally meant to house recent converts to Catholicism. The Pasig River flows through this city, and a ring highway around it nicknamed “EDSA” names a 1986 revolution whose leaders included (20 pts)",
        "Cardinal Jaime Sin. This city was connected by the first permanent route across the Pacific Ocean to Acapulco in New Spain. Except for a stint from 1948 to 1976 by (10 pts)",
        "Quezon City, this city has served as a capital for centuries. The People Power Revolution toppled Ferdinand Marcos in, for ten points, what capital city of the Philippines?"
      ],
      "answer": "Manila"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This family’s first ruler was pressured to retire to the Stoudion monastery on the advice of Michael Psellos. A history of this family was written by Anna and describes the suspicion this family held towards (20 pts)",
        "Bohemond of Taranto. This family’s most famous ruler sent his ambassadors to the Council of Piacenza after a defeat at (10 pts)",
        "Manzikert. In response to Seljuk expansion, Pope Urban II called for knights to come aid this family. For ten points, name this Byzantine ruling family that, during the First Crusade, was led by Alexius I."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Komnenos dynasty",
        "Komnenids",
        "Komnenoi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A popular piece of propaganda during this scandal was the fabricated story of a boy being stabbed with a bayonet while trying to save his bunny. Pelham Glassford resigned as police superintendent in the wake of this event. Future generals (20 pts)",
        "Patton, MacArthur, and Eisenhower were among the forces called to action in this event, which took place on the Anacostia Flats. (10 pts)",
        "Herbert Hoover was heavily criticized for his response to, for ten points, what “expeditionary force” of twenty thousand men who, in 1932, demanded early payment of their World War I service certificates?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Bonus Army",
        "Bonus Expeditionary Force"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first holder of this post lasted only thirteen days in power after William Fox defeated Henry Sewell in election. Holders of this post refused to accept the autonomy offered in the 1931 Statute of Westminster until George (20 pts)",
        "Forbes took power. Finland’s Sanna Marin beat a record set by the current holder of this post as the world’s youngest female leader. This office was held for thirteen years by Richard (10 pts)",
        "Seddon, who used his tenure to annex the Cook Islands and buy land from the native Maori. Jacinda Ardern currently holds, for ten points, what post that heads a government in Wellington?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Prime Minister of New Zealand",
        "premier of New Zealand"
      ]
    }
  ]
}